hey folks welcome back to the Dark Horse
podcast livestream complete with dog
tail all right we are back to answer
your super chat questions we had with
dog tail and drinks yes some people said
that they had enjoyed us more when we
were drinking at the point that one of
our previous live streams had run into
trouble and we had taken up drinking to
see if that would help so what we've
done is given that it is undoubtedly 5
o'clock somewhere maybe even here we
have gotten something to drink we have
put the kids to bed they were not happy
about that in light of the fact that we
have not yet had dinner but anyway they
went once we properly threatened them so
anyway they're in bed and and we are now
free to talk to you about anything and
everything sex drugs rock and roll it's
all on the menu ok alright so we'll do
what we've done the last several of it
is we can spend about an hour here we'll
take the first half hour to respond to
as many of these questions from the
super chat from the previous live stream
as possible and then take the second
half hour to respond in the order they
come in likely unless we reject any out
of hand the questions from the second
super chat ok so the first one from echo
points to an article on mosquito fish
for which female but not male brain size
is greater following selection for
longer going to podium so this I will
say we are going to take a look at and
respond to in the next live stream ok
second question regarding culture and
consciousness so this is a reference in
part to the talk that we gave for
Princeton via webinar last Wednesday six
days ago now and is now up on the web so
regarding cultural and consciousness
could psychoactive fungi have played a
role in ancient peoples ability to
quickly make diverse and novel insights
and why many just didn't cultures have
emerged so quickly
and answer the first part of the
question absolutely absolutely this is
you know hallucinogenic I think I think
we at least alluded to this in that very
brief talk that we gave when we compared
you know said culture is to
consciousness
as the sacred is to the shamanistic as
orthodoxy is to heterodoxy as
conservatism is to progressivism to this
yeah I would just add that many many
cultures access that state of mind
however they do it whether they do it
with sweat lodges or hunger or other
extreme things or they access it
chemically but they wouldn't be doing it
if it didn't have a value that more than
compensated them for the cost of it and
the caught' cost is significant because
the fact is those states fascinating as
they may be are not clear-headed states
it's not something that you want the
captain of the ship involved in while
the captain is navigating in dangerous
waters so yes it must be adaptive and
anyway look for further discussions of
that here and in our book absolutely
with regard to the second part of the
question though why many distinct
cultures have emerged so quickly I'm
less confident of that unless a culture
finds itself fashioning among the lines
of some people follow a particular of
shamans insights or encouragement to
take a particular psychoactive substance
biet fungi or something else because it
it seems to me that it might take a
little longer
upon exploring a new environment to come
to a stable relationship with a
psychoactive that exists there yeah
that's true although there are some
cultures that have a long-standing
relationship with a particular
psychoactive and in fact go on
pilgrimages which could happen in other
words a population that was in motion
across the land could traverse it to the
same location to collect their peyote or
whatever in fact
the image that we showed when we were
talking about culture and consciousness
being an analogous relationship with for
instance the sacredness shamanistic in
that Princeton talk was a yarn painting
from a Huichol shaman and Huichol is
exactly the culture that you're talking
about that do these law everyone in the
culture at some point is expected or
encouraged to go on with these very long
pilgrimages the end place of which is
hallucinogenic and Theo genic
exploration yep
all right next question is there any
evolutionary advantage for the
decussation of nerve fibers that is the
crossing of nerve fibers from one side
of the body to the other that is to say
the right hemisphere controls the left
side of the body I would say it very
likely passes the adaptive test in other
words there's a cost even at just a
trivial level of the nerves having to
travel a further distance and therefore
the rate of transmission on those nerve
nerve fibers being reduced slightly
probably suggests an adaptive function
the only competing hypothesis I would
imagine is that there is a historical
constraint but I believe we see the
pattern too frequently for historical
constraint to explain all the examples
of it so that's not an ironclad answer
but I would say my instinct says yes
it's going to have an adaptive value and
I do I cannot somehow free this in my
mind from the question of the brakes of
a car being hooked up crossways so your
front left and your right rear brake are
connected together so yeah your agency
with control there's more there's more
control in this sort of arrangement than
in just having two sides completely
going parallel so the decussation is is
a word that actually I wasn't
particularly familiar with even though
talk comparative anatomy for many many
years
but like the chiasma the ear the
crossing from one side to the other is I
think and I'm not a hundred percent sure
of this but basically we have bilateral
symmetry you know left left animals that
have a left and a right that you could
fold in the middle along an axis of
symmetry and basically get a mirror
image starting
basil vertebrates and then separately in
arthropod lineages right so insects and
such and spiders and and then separately
again in a few other lineages but if we
take vertebrates in particular you get
brains pretty quickly after you get
bilateral symmetry and this idea of
lateralization of things happening on
the left side and not the right and vice
versa it doesn't take too much longer
before it shows up and I think that that
key asthma the crossing is ancient as
well so it looks to me therefore like
it's going to add some stability and
that stability might just be a kind of
like error correction like you know just
like you say with regard to brakes of
the car like if one part fails you're
more likely to have things from far
afield I'm sort of controlling what's
what's good argument right there is
damage might you know if you're damaged
on this side having the control
apparatus on the side where you weren't
just hit you could see an advantage to
that yeah and I'm wondering if there's
not just some sort of danger of
feedbacks you know if you had the right
side controlling the right side if you
wouldn't be in danger of getting some
kind of loop that might create a I don't
know policy or whatever yeah it is yeah
that's good okay next question can you
please show the bear skull and this is
the bear no that's the bear skull and
toxiel bear phylogeny is the
evolutionary cost of consciousness
though purely metabolic and our other
and almost conscious okay so we got a
couple questions here so we did bring up
we saw this question enough to bring up
they're both bare skulls both pairs
given you owe him more than that yes I
don't know either but my guess is having
asked that question this person knows
full well our perspective on this which
is that seals are bears for the same
reason by the same linguistic rigor that
we would say that monkeys are mammals if
is X a Y is the same kind of question is
a monkey a mammal of course it is what
else would it be is a seal a bear yes it
is what else would it be
because seals as far as we
understand it evolved from bears there
within the category bear the same way
monkey is within the category mammal and
so there's a there's this phylogenetic
analysis which is exactly what the
question asks with regard to what's the
relationship between seals and bears and
seals appear by every every type of
character that's been looked at at this
point
morphological molecular developmental
all of these character sets run in the
same direction and say yep seals evolved
from bears and that makes seals Bears in
the same way that makes monkeys mammals
maybe maybe in some ways the more
interesting question is whoa seals went
back to the water secondarily you know
we all emerge from the water when
tetrapods first came out many hundreds
of millions millions of years ago but
within mammals and this is this is far
afield but this is this is the sort of
thing that I could talk about forever we
have four different evolutions of
returns to water in mammals and only one
of those returns to water which is say
the pinnipeds the seals sea lions and
walrus derived from bears we have also
the whales which derived from points
living clay right so whales are emerging
from hippopotamuses that's that's one of
the other two returns to the sea we have
otters which are embedded within the
carnivorans now so our otters otters
must be peeled for more can't afford
they are weasels which are known as
their kina form yeah so broadly speaking
the chronitons or branch into two types
the sort of cat-like and the doglike so
otters are in that doglike branch and
then we have the manatees and manatees
are related to elephant Citians yes so
for totally different emergencies of
secondarily aquatic mammals so I realize
calling you out on this on air it's good
probably a terrible thing to do but now
that you say you said for returns to the
water but I'm thinking you know otters
is an edge case oh for sure right it's a
return to the sea yep
mmm seals sea lions and whoa
they're an edge case in some ways as
well because they return to land to
breathe well right so whales are fully
Mounties are fully pen apes' are kind of
an otters edgy ER but as long as we're
taking the edge cases then we've got a
bunch of other edge cases too because
we've got muskrats and Desmond's and
I've forgotten there's a Cuban rodent
that is aquatic and those are not all
one clade of we kind of went aquatic and
we're rodents mmm no oh and then there's
there's beavers of course all right um
so anyway these are all interesting edge
cases and the you know the otter if we
say returns to the sea otter the sea
otter gets us there yep the sea otter
was not likely to have been first so
it's likely to have come from a river
otter which was partially terrestrial
sea otters are almost entirely aquatic
yep but anyway now we have digressed
rather fully lost a quarter of the
audience right there is the evolution of
the second part of this question was is
the evolutionary cost of consciousness
purely metabolic and our other animals
conscious know the cost of consciousness
goes well beyond metabolic one so we are
defining consciousness as we defined it
in our talk the other night which is
that fraction of cognition that is
packaged for exchange that we are not
going to redo that talk here but there
are all sorts of costs to being
conscious one of them I would argue is
confusion there are a lot of things that
you can be programmed to detect and
respond to even intelligently without
being conscious once you're conscious
you're in grave danger of choking in the
sense of you're up to bat and you become
too conscious and you can't hit the ball
right now starfish don't choke no they
don't I've never seen it happen so
anyway yes right there we have okay so
starfish don't satisfy our rubric for
are they conscious but is their
consciousness and other organisms such
as quickly identify a few oh wait I
wanted to say one was one more cost here
which is a conscious brain is a large
brain and large brains are more
vulnerable so you got metabolic you've
got danger and you've got confusion and
I would say that's just the beginning of
the list so yes consciousness is a a
costly thing it might be beneficial in
order to justify the large brains are
also a metabolic cost oh yes it costs
better run also there but built into the
question yeah so other animals that have
consciousness maybe we'll just name a
few and then we will encourage more of
this conversation later domestic dogs
but also wolves toothed whales including
dolphins and orca elephants other
primates Lions maybe parrots corvids not
covitz corvids which includes crows
probably hyenas yep there are lots of
things but what are those things that
are long-lived large-brained have
generational overlap are social as they
live in social groups and they know each
other and have long developmental
periods which in humans we call
childhoods but we are not saying these
things are as conscious as people
there's sort of a question about what
fraction of your cognition is in the
conscious realm and this varies a lot
and it's not synonymous with
intelligence so anyway more on that
later and elsewhere I'm a stylist salons
already follow zero sanitation fungus
very I which may or may not be the
plural of virus but I like it fungus
very high bacteria combined with cuts
and hair slivers and bodily fluids huge
air movement bad ventilation should hair
salons open yet I would not be opening
the hair salons yet if it were me I
would be opening other things before
hair salons but people are going nuts
over the lack of haircuts I feel like
you're trying to tell me something
yeah this is a tough question yeah I
think the real question is that I don't
know what the answer is here there is a
tremendous danger in any of these very
intimate kinds of businesses I don't
know what we're all gonna do at some
point maybe we just begin to tolerate
each other's crazy hair which is a day
I've been looking forward to for a long
time
but anyway it's it's a tough puzzle but
the important thing now that we've
discovered that our HVAC systems are
probably giving people the flu
look the flu kills people every year why
are we comfortable with the fact that
our HVAC systems are spreading it now
suddenly we're on that page people now
are suddenly aware of the fact that
there's a certain art to washing your
hands so that it actually works right
let's not go back to just washing them
kind of pro forma yeah so what should a
hair salon look like so that this isn't
the case yes how can they change in the
future and for right now though at least
for those of us in the northern
hemisphere
certainly I've heard talk of there's
there are a lot of jurisdictions that
are closing down streets to car traffic
to enable people to social distance
while being outside and this will
potentially allow for restaurants to
reopen at some point for something other
than takeout and have people sit outside
to eat other kinds of businesses like
hair salons maybe could also be doing
some of their business outside for in
the northern hemisphere as we move into
you know late spring and summer if
you're in Australia this is going to be
harder and harder and obviously you know
weather is highly variable so it doesn't
it's not easy but it is part of my toe
so every you get used to when you travel
in a lot of the rest of the world that
doesn't have such controlled interior
spaces where you have to have a lot of
air flow and you expect to not beat
exactly the temperature that you were
counting on for the entire part of your
day yeah so I would say maybe an
assignment for those of you in the
audience for whom this is your specialty
figure out how to deliver haircuts over
zoom and I think you'd have to early
investors
that's on the reports of 1902 backhoe
users question 1 smoking bans cause them
to spend more time outside could this be
a factor in the strikingly small
percentage of hospitalized smokers
that's really interesting we've talked
on one of the earlier live streams and
I'm sorry we've done enough now that I
no longer remember mostly which number
it was in but one of the earlier live
streams had the title smoking in in that
the name smoking in the titles would be
relatively easy to find we talked about
what we thought it was understood at
that point but smoking bans causing
smokers to spend more time outside it
could be a factor it doesn't seem to me
that smokers spend so much time outside
that it would be fully explanatory but
it might be partially explanatory what
do you think it's obviously a potential
factor and one of the things that we're
discovering in this pandemic is just how
complex the interaction of factors is I
mean you know it's Subway's but it's
local trains you know that's the kind of
level of detail that we need to be
thinking so yeah it's a good thought and
maybe must all of our scientific
information come from peer-reviewed
articles parentheses received pushback
on the medium article presumably the one
that we were talking about to
livestreams ago
what makes China's style of wet market
more or less dangerous than
western-style factory farming for
viruses yeah so all of this this is two
distinct and very important points both
of which we have spent some time talking
about we talked about peer review I
think in six actually a fair bit
livestream six and then we also talked a
bit about wet markets early on when it
still seemed like that was the most
likely source for this virus but
western-style factory farming is
absolutely a hundred percent going to
contribute to some superbugs at least
the difference is you don't have in
factory farming exotic meats being
brought into human cuisine that haven't
been there for a long time so I would
add a couple things here one just a bit
of history the first time we ever heard
of the novel coronavirus we had just
emerged from the Amazon where we had
spent ten days almost su and we'd come
out and it was we were in Ecuador we
were taking a couple days in the otavalo
region up in the Andes and a news story
about novel coronavirus came across the
phone somehow because there was one case
thought to be in Ecuador and at that
point I looked into it and it looked
very much like what markets were the
obvious thing and I looked at the
question of which bats it was and and
all of that and I tweeted something
about thinking the wet market hypothesis
seemed likely and I immediately got
pushback from people who pointed out the
job advertisement for the wuhan virology
lab and I immediately retracted my claim
that it made sense that it was wet
markets because there was obviously much
I did not know about the situation but
in any case we can't trust the
peer-reviewed literature because the
peer-reviewed literature comes from a
group that has the same bias - what's
happening over there that cat has broken
into our house again
so anyway the the problem with the
peer-reviewed literature one of the many
problems with it is that the people who
generate it come through channels that
cause them to have the same biases and
while the scientific method should
correct for that it often does not so we
have to engage in the contemplation of
things that emerge outside of the peer
reviewed literature and the question
should be are they well done are they
done well enough that they could be in
the peer reviewed literature of the peer
reviewed literature was better all right
there was another part to that question
it was about peer review and wet markets
and I think I think you are more or less
dangerous than western-style factory
fire for viruses so I did want to say
something about this factory farming
business we are very anti factory
farming there's a long list of reasons
that it's not healthy it's not
justifiable from the point of view of
the treatment of the animals it's
healthy in terms of the product it
creates and it's not sanitary but the
danger of pathogens is actually quite
dependent on things like the form that
the meat comes in and how it is treated
so I made a tweet that I think many must
have regarded is curious earlier this
week when I said that I thought it might
be that ground beef was finished as a
result of the kovat 19:00 epidemic and
the reason that I singled out ground
beef and believe me I like a good
hamburger as much as the next guy but
the problem with ground beef is that it
takes particles that are on the outside
of the meat and it mixes them in and the
only way to purify what's inside the
meat is to cook it hot enough that those
things would be killed and so a rare
hamburger takes whatever pathogens were
on the outside of this thing if somebody
had some illness coughed into the meat
as it was being ground sold it and then
you served the hamburger raw well you're
gonna be getting that pathogen in an
environment that's actually quite well
suited to protect it and there's just no
way to make that safe if you grind your
own beef does it solve the problem
partly but not completely because still
you're taking things that are on the
outside and moving them inside so the
point is if you have a steak you're
heating the outside hot enough and the
inside is protected by virtue of the
fact that it's on the inside these are
not inherent to factory farming factory
farming is bad it caused the spongiform
encephalopathy crisis Mad Cow by virtue
of feeding animals things they shouldn't
have been eating like the brains of
other animals but factory farming is bad
there's no end to reasons we should halt
the practice but it is not the culprit
it's a culprit our friend Holly math
nerd asks please explain how living in a
reliably blue or lively red state should
affect attempts at game theory analyses
on who to vote for
well people our age remember the 96
election when some of us wanted to send
a message that we weren't pleased with
Clinton but didn't feel comfortable
handing
that point handing the presidency to a
Republican and so traded votes if we
were living in blue states traded votes
with people in other states such that we
could send a message while not
necessarily changing the election I'd
say we're in a very different place now
I think we were in a very different
place then we just didn't know it yet
and we're in it so we're in the same
place as we were then well let's put it
this way there has always been a defect
in the idea of trading votes to send a
message which is that to the extent that
your antagonist and bi antagonist I mean
something like the DNC for us actual
Democrats to the extent that they know
that you're going to trade votes so you
don't hurt the candidate they want to
elect they have no reason to pay
attention to you and so the problem is
they have cynically chosen a scenario in
which those of us who want to see
progress are going to be left with
something unpalatable but better than
the alternative on the other side
knowing that we will then come flocking
to them
and my point would be at some point you
have to stop participating in that
cynical game and when you do that will
you hurt the Democratic Party of course
you will but it was they who chose to
engage in this game of chicken and
responding rationally and I would argue
responding such that maybe two elections
down the road three elections down the
road you're no longer subject to that
game is necessary does that mean it's
costless no it's very dangerous and
destructive but they haven't left us a
better option so the fact that we choose
a bad option when we don't have a better
one shouldn't surprise anyone always
more to be said there but I think we're
going to move on for now the next one
Brett I feel like I've talked to you in
an elevator at the Portland La Quinta
somewhere between September November
2018 which would have been just after we
moved to Portland
were you there then or am I just
tripping I was the big bearded guy with
a German Shepherd yep I hang out in that
elevator Thanks wait what's a look
Quinta it's a hotel chain
can't imagine I was in a hotel in
Portland after we moved here with a
German Shepherd it's a it's possible
that there was some something and I'm
going to remember later why I was there
but it doesn't ring a bell I don't
remember the German Shepherd and big
bearded guys being a dime a dozen but
German Shepherd is that you'd remember
German Shepherd in an elevator I
remember now
thank you from the UK if your commentary
thank you an event horizon may be an
evolutionary bottleneck conversation
protection absolutely excellent tonight
many thanks thank you for that an
evolutionary bottleneck of what sort do
you think well it could be coming you
know I the problem because it's an event
horizon the point is we don't know what
happens next and one of the things that
is certainly worrying me is that a lot
of the politicization of this
circumstance has a kind of
saber-rattling element to it and while I
think even though the hypothesis that
this virus came from the lab in Wuhan is
much more credible than the mainstream
press has given it credit for the
meaning of it having come and come from
that lab is not at all what the Trump
administration for example seems to be
suggesting in other words it could well
be a scientific error which would be
very much worth our time to consider but
it's not as troubling as the Chinese
government is it is not inherently their
fault if the NIH was also participating
in furthering the research that may have
created this problem yeah what are both
your thoughts on Justin Amash I have not
yet heard his name spoken so I'm not
sure I'm not butchering the
pronunciation but Justin Amash as I
understand it is I think a Michigan
maybe former Republican who has just
declared that he is going to run for
hoping for maybe he's already been
accepted as but I'm hoping for the top
spot on the libertarian ticket he wants
to be he thinks that he can do better
than either of the Republican or the
Democrat and there's already pushed back
of course saying he's going to be a
spoiler and if he runs it's going to be
Trump who's in office for another four
years
yeah well would he be the spoiler or is
Joe Biden the spoiler I mean yeah really
I this is the problem and I would argue
yeah I think this guy is no Nader but
he's he's gonna end up taking the hit
even though Biden seems to be a non
contender yeah I go really it's
incumbent on the Democratic Party to
field candidates good enough that they
win by a large margin and to the extent
that they've been fielding candidates
who to the extent they win win by a
narrow margin that's on them not on the
would be alternatives you know I'm not a
huge fan of the libertarian party
libertarianism is a philosophy that
doesn't take you very far
and I think the kovat 19 M epidemic
reveals much of the folly behind that
philosophy even if there's an element of
it that I agree with that the
instantiation just doesn't cut it
so I don't know III don't know him in
particular and I I'm already a bit
skeptical of this approach but I do
think we need an approach and maybe soon
enough we will sit down with some more
drinks and talk about something that's
actually viable sounds good 30 minutes
okay we're gonna try to rush through a
few more of these because there are some
no we're just gonna do it and then we'll
switch over okay Zack do you think oh do
you think coronavirus will remain in a
person's cells for lifetime like I've
seen bar or is it expelled
we just don't know and I don't know that
I have an opinion on this at this point
yeah it's not really expelled what
really happens behind the scenes is that
cells that contain the virus are
either self destroy through a process
called apoptosis or are killed by cells
that are trained to recognize them
whether this remains in the system like
one of the viruses that hides inside of
neurons and things we don't know I would
say of all the things that we could know
about this virus that we don't know yet
this is what I'm eager to know and I'm I
don't think it's going to turn out to be
a persistent lifelong recurring thing
but if it was that would be very bad
news
given takedowns of people question
authorities have you considered syncing
to an alternative decentralized platform
like lb ry they make it pretty easy I'm
not familiar with lb ry off the top of
my head we certainly are interested in
looking for an alternative but of course
every time you switch you introduce more
complexity into your world so you can
categorize us as lb ry q curious we are
curious except yours doesn't start with
you it's questioning that's right you
introduced curious into the discussion
I'm going to plead ignorance okay fair
enough
well I I think we might describe
ourselves as ellaby ry curious though
rather than lb ry q questioning fair in
requesting their questioning know how to
deal with family that promotes ideas
like masks don't work masks cause Borum
than good bill gates as a murderer wants
to microchip us all with his vaccines
and I do my own research I'm sorry look
so let me just say we really want to you
know move through so we get to some from
the next Super chat but one thing early
and this this wouldn't work right now
but Tucker Carlson was actually pretty
early you pointed out to me I don't I
wish I knew the date on this but he did
kind of a diatribe a very careful
diatribe and when she was definitely
speaking to his base but he said long
before the Trump administration was
doing anything appropriate in this
regard basically speaking to his his
audience said this is actually for real
serious and you all need to take it
seriously and yes the left has gone off
the rails and is arguing about what to
call it and getting all upset about
people calling up the Chinese virus and
the Luhan virus and all of this but do
not confuse that reaction with the idea
that there's nothing real here
and the fact that he did that was a
wonderful and important and valuable and
it also gave people a thing that they
could say you know what here's someone
who is often speaking to your priors who
is saying something that doesn't match
what you think is true please listen to
this and I don't know exactly what the
equivalent of that is right now you know
we we tried to speak to people across
you know across the aisle as it were and
you know are quite willing to mock the
extremists on both sides but basically
the vast majority of those of us who
aren't super woke or you know racist
fools are we're interested in willing to
talk to I don't know if I have much more
than that for right now well I think
you're very much on the right track and
Tucker Carlson is one of these people
who is a capable of seeing a great many
of these difficult points and be capable
of saying them and surviving what comes
back I'm reminded when when you and I
were kids the saying was only Nixon
could go to China that anybody was
further left than Nixon would have been
accused of having communist sympathies
or something but the Nixon could do it
and in fact did yeah and Tucker Carlson
also has the ability to say all kinds of
things about you know I mean I've heard
him say things that I thought were
dead-on accurate about class warfare and
its meaning in the US and that it has
taken place and that it has had big
impacts and all of that so anyway yes
figuring out who you can pay attention
to on the other side who is not only
hero bowl but insightful yeah so I know
Greg Gutfeld just had a big day and
extraordinary ratings beat the other
shows in his timeslot he's another
person who is he's also on a box right
but also on Fox capable of crossing the
aisle and very intelligent guy so anyway
yeah figure out who you can listen to on
the
other side and then make a point of
doing it and then your own perspective
becomes richer but I mean the question
is how do you deal with family all right
so you know in Kurt finding those people
and but get encouraging family to listen
to or watch viewpoints that they have
already become entrenched against is
tougher yeah it's a tougher sell I would
say I don't mean this cynically but turn
it into a game right there's always a
question about can you is there a divide
that you are not supposed to be able to
cross that you can figure out how to
cross and you know over time you get
better at it and the divides that you
can cross are larger and it's very
rewarding in fact you will find actually
you feel richer and happier when the
circle of people that you can relate to
has grown and you know don't include bad
people but frankly bad people aren't a
large percentage of the population
they're important but they're not a big
percentage most people are mistaken
about some things you're mistaken about
some things and figuring out how you can
cross those divides and discover what
you don't know that you should and teach
people something that they should know
that they don't it's it's incredibly
rewarding isn't the reduction in subway
schedule similarly as dreadful as
reducing grocery store hours of
operation make the resource more scarce
increase its necessity thanks from a
reasonable Republican yes exactly right
and thank you for that question it's
exactly it's not even really analogous
it's the same thing yep and just two
more questions then we'll skip we'll
switch to the questions from this live
stream knowing those at risk could be an
argument for opening the economy the
number of lives lost due to the shutdown
is an unknown economies or chaotic
systems thus not predictable gambling
the government can provide essential
resources should we suffer an economic
collapse as a fool's wager I'm not sure
I totally understand well I mean I think
it's you know it's a I think pretty well
stated case for your you've got costs
either way
let's be adult and let's not imagine
that because we can be sentimental about
people whose names we will know we will
know they've died of Kovac 19 don't
imagine that you're not creating harm on
the other side that might be greater
that's true I think what is spooking a
lot of us who understand what it means
for a virus to have jumped the gap into
humans to have created an almost
instantaneous pandemic and to have much
about it that we don't know is that the
downside of this disease spreading
further is potentially immense I mean
just think for a second about your own
argument and then ask yourself the
question what if for one reason or
another we cannot rid ourselves of Cyrus
Cove too and kovat 19 becomes an annual
phenomenon let's say that it diminishes
in harm for various reasons down to what
the flu currently produces well now
you've got two flus you had one I'm not
saying the flu is one thing but I mean
every year you have flu circulating if
you're gonna have flu circulating and
you're gonna have kovat 19 circulating
in whatever new form it takes that's a
major hit that humanity just took so
what you don't want to do is let this
thing get any further advanced than it
has gotten you want to leave it at as
much disadvantage as you can so that
your options are greatest to do
something about it so you're comparing
what you're calling an economic collapse
but the fact is we don't have an
economic collapse yet and we do have
places to go in order to prevent that
collapse from happening so are there
resources we can draw on that do not
force us to allow this virus to spread
without restriction maybe there are and
it's probably worth it because the
downside of being stuck with this
disease for many years or perhaps
indefinitely is very large any thoughts
on the murder wasps
it's terrifying it's like it's it's the
it's the plagues all right so these uh
these giant wasps have come out of China
I guess or somewhere in Asia
I call them Chinese Communist Party
wasps of course you too and I guess
we're gonna switch to the other question
so we'll just take a minute here but one
thing that's super interesting is that
like all invasive species like all
introduced species that settle in and
become a problem the would-be
competitors and the prey of the thing in
the new environment have no idea what to
do with it so honeybees here in the
Pacific Northwest we're in Washington
state where the murder wasps have been
have been found are defenseless they
have no idea what to do they get torn
apart they get eaten their heads ripped
off their hives destroyed and as if the
honeybees weren't having a hard enough
time and we rely many of our food
systems rely on honeybee pollinators so
this is this is a huge huge problem that
said in the place where the murder wasps
are native the bees that the murder the
murder wasps would eat have figured out
a way to deal with them and they huddle
around them and they basically choke
them they fixate them by increasing the
amount of co2 in the little bubble that
they create around them and they
increase the temperature and those two
things basically kill the murder wasp
so the bee is in wherever it is exactly
these murder watches are from have
behaviorally figured out a defense
against them and of course in the place
where there is no history of murder
wasps the bees are naive just like all
of humanity was naive the coronavirus
six months ago eight months ago at this
point and we had no idea what to do
hopefully we're figuring it out how is
it that the local honeybees could be
taught how to deal with the murder wasps
I don't know if it's possible but bees
teach each other they actually show
how to find stuff through their wild
ancestors yeah hell of a waggle dance to
explain this one yeah so I should point
out just as long as you're engaging the
full complexity of this our honeybees
are also invaders yes these are not
native now I am very much in favor of
the honeybees being rescued for many
reasons they may actually be the same
species yeah it could be which means
that you could potentially introduce
this it's actually the same species then
you can introduce the behaviorally
changes and I'm much more worried
frankly about whatever else it is
probably pesticides that are causing the
spectacular decrease in honeybees and
potentially driving their hives crazy
and things like that but the real point
here is invasive species are a
tremendous hazard right the murder wasp
thing is just at the beginning but the
problem is once these things get
sufficiently advanced there's nothing to
be done about them so maybe maybe maybe
a high level of vigilance at the moment
would allow us to address the murder
wasps and get rid of them so that they
did not do what will otherwise be
inevitable which is naturalized into all
of our habitats but yeah it's it's
frightening and they are they're also
amazing but I don't really want to meet
one here okay so how much time to be a
blip SEC okay we're gonna go through as
many of these questions from the current
live stream as we can is the hypothesis
that Sweden's strategy will allow them
to forego a follow-up way of correct
we have no idea don't know I doubt it
but we have no idea don't know for one
thing it's not just a strategy there is
a lot of variation between places that
is functioning as noise here and we
really don't know enough how do you
suppose that if Biden gets replaced at
the DNC elite don't pick his replacement
how does a game be a solution not equal
a viable third party maybe it does equal
a viable third party or maybe it
involves one of the third parties that
actually exists deciding to change
strategies there there are viable path
forward all of them are going to sound
implausible at first so suspend your
disbelief enough to consider them could
a meritocracy ever supplanted democracy
an astronaut styled multidimensional
dimensional stress test of candidates
free from DNC GOP interference also
Brett your hair is a celebration of
freedom in lockdown hell yeah I don't
know what that means what I like it I
don't I don't understand a contrast
between meritocracy and democracy I
don't a democracy ought to be a
meritocracy we clearly aren't there we
aim to be there though well here's the
thing I think I see something here which
is a well-functioning market is a
meritocracy a democracy could administer
a market such that it functioned well
this is sort of the ideal actually of a
game B scenario is that we would create
the landscape of incentives such that
the market would do an excellent job of
creating value without creating harm and
that that would elevate people who were
exhibiting merit so there would end up
being disparities and wealth but they
would be the result of having produced
well-being which is actually that's sort
of the mythology of our market that our
market doesn't really work that way it
produces an awful lot of harm so anyway
I do think that they can coexist I don't
know that the meritocracy supplants the
democracy but I think they play
different roles a friend who went to
Evergreen attacked me for joining the
Peace Corps saying it was neo-colonial I
didn't get the hate until I saw your
vice video mmm yeah I'll just say that
there was a lot to recommend evergreen
and that the students that we had almost
to a person were open-minded and capable
of doing extraordinary things and many
of them did did that and we are still in
touch with many of them and as we have
noted many times elsewhere it was not
our students who turned on Brett and
then us it was other people who were
sent by
ylan tension faculty and a few staff
members who created that problem and so
your friend who went to Evergreen had
presumably been indoctrinated rather
than educated which was unfortunately
quite possible there and still is I
imagine but it was not the it was not
necessarily the student body that was
the problem
yeah I loved the idea of the Peace Corps
is neo-colonial and I think actually the
idea that peace might be neo-colonial is
next so look for it well if math is
evidence the patriarchy thesis evidence
it's all in keeping right yeah so Dark
Horse moderator is asking on behalf of
Nobel Prize winner
professor montagnier says the virus
structure was interfered with is there
anything on that front if we were trying
to create a shift people holding under
the power would strategize question mark
yeah let me speak this a little bit to
the extent that you hear the idea that
this virus was altered by human beings
and you think that that is the other
side advancing a conspiracy theory
there's a lot wrong with that there is
plenty of reason to entertain the
possibility that this virus was altered
and if you do that and you do it with an
open mind you will find that there's
actually a substantial amount of
evidence that suggests not only is it
possible but that it would solve a
number of the mysteries surrounding the
virus as we find it so I'm not saying
that it is true but I am saying we have
several highly highly positioned
scientists who are in a position to
understand the details of the genetics
and the biochemistry who find the
hypothesis that the virus was altered
incredible unless you know more than
they do you should probably leave the
possibility open at least thoughts on
the scientific validity of evopsych us
ike being a stand-in for evolutionary
psychology
it holds great promise there is good
foundation of illusionary thinking at
its at its base it is too often wielded
uncaring and therefore inaccurately and
not merely and precisely so it is too
easy to dismiss because many of the
people doing the work don't quite know
the limits and the need to focus on
prediction and falsifiability I would
say I'd say it's the right question but
that the history is that it's been too
timid and not imaginary enough to get to
the full answer so it's hopeful but I'm
frustrated that were held to small
questions rather than big ones what are
your thoughts about vouching not having
a client since 1984 about 40 years ago I
worry that he only sees numbers and not
people who defines the optimal you know
that that doesn't particularly bother me
the fact of a doctor who isn't a
practicing clinician who doesn't
actively see patients doesn't inherently
mean that he doesn't have insight into
what is good for people there are a lot
of different ways to gain insight and
you know we the equivalent over in our
space is that an academia research is
active research with big grant monies is
prioritized much more than teaching when
of course universities are supposedly
about teaching students and so it is the
the fact of him not having patients for
40 years doesn't inherently mean that
he's that he doesn't know what he's
doing I think there are other reasons to
think that some of what he is suggesting
is suspect and he may have some
interests that are not above board but
the fact if I'm not having patients
isn't one of them when you say
consciousness do you mean subjective
experience all on Nagle your description
of consciousness sounds more like
metacognition that subjective experience
is that right and just quickly to the
definition and maybe people directly to
the Princeton talk there's a reason that
we have defined it the way we have which
is that fraction of cognition that is
packaged for exchange and that is
deuced from the way people seem to mean
consciousness when they invoke it in
other words when people say that they
are conscious of something how
frequently does it fit in that category
and it seems to fit well subjective
experience is implied by this and one of
the things that we talked briefly about
in our Princeton talk and we'll talk
more about elsewhere is the reason that
subjective experience would be coupled
with the fact of a cognitive thought
being packaged for exchange right those
two things are related but it may not be
obvious why it has to do with more or
less why it is that we are designed to
exchange thoughts between individuals
what we do with that capacity and the
necessity of having a subjective
experience that allows you to compare
your thought but somebody else's thought
to hold them both in mind and have a
place where they can be juxtaposed so
anyway I hope that was a decent answer
good why did we evolve hate why do we
evolve hate you know this this is one of
these questions where it's not obvious
to me why it wouldn't be obvious why we
need hate right we need hate in order I
mean it doesn't have to be called hate
maybe it could be designed in other ways
and you could feel it differently but we
need something that allows us to
categorize a certain number of things
and figure out how to oppose them I
think the problem is hate gets a bad
name because often it is opposed to
things that don't need to be opposed and
therefore it seems like a corruption but
at some level I wonder if what's going
on is that you need something that
functions this way and when it is miss
applied it gets named and discussed and
when it is not miss applied it goes
without notice and maybe that's the way
to fix it I don't know what this next
question means but I said I'd read them
in order so here it goes how much money
does the audience need to raise for
science for Brett to get a perm what
makes you think I don't have a problem
yeah many Americans I don't know the
Animus find out many Americans are tired
of the professional politician in quotes
what do you two want to see on the
resume of a candidate presidential
candidate what do you want what do you
two want to see on the resume of a
presidential candidate I think resume is
the wrong approach but there are some
characteristics that I think I'm amazed
that we don't demand them before you
answer let me say that much like my
answer about vouch E and like your
description of plan B and our
description of the fourth frontier in
which you can't map it out and say
exactly what you're looking for you're
looking to get on a Foothill I would say
there are a lot of different ways that
you can get there but having been driven
from an early age to be in a position of
power and having that be really your
claim to fame is unlikely to be a
diverse enough set of drives and
experiences to make you an excellent
leader but beyond that there going to be
a lot of different ways that you can get
there um you said Plan B did I yes you
did oh no no we hate those guys just
they're almost as bad as the people's
front of Judea or sup the popular
peoples from it is know so let's just
say this a president I do not care
personally we're on the political
spectrum a president is at the moment
there are errors in which I might but at
the moment I want somebody who's very
smart I want somebody who is self
skeptical who is patriotic and who is
capable of playing well with others if
you have those characteristics as far as
I'm concerned we should elect you right
it doesn't matter if you come from the
right or come from the left because
those things would cause you to behave
in certain ways relative to the way the
nation is governed that would be very
positive for us and the place where we
part company if you're on the right and
have those characteristics the place
where we actually differ over what
should happen next is far down the road
so let's get there let's put the
patriotism first let's get somebody
who's clever enough to understand how
difficult this puzzle is into the office
and let's give them give them some some
leash two questions could you talk about
your female coyness theory from
evolution perspective
let me just asterisk that and say that's
not really ours but we can talk more
about that but maybe we should save that
in front of the time because I'm sure it
will come up frequently and when do you
plan to share your male gayness theory
Bret um that's a good question you know
yeah back in the day which is to say
months ago I was inclined to figure out
how to rent a hall and deploy that
hypothesis so that people could
entertain it and evaluate it maybe
upload it later for viewing sure of
course of course problem is renting a
hall does that still exist is that a
thing yeah but it will again it will it
will so you say this is the reason that
I wanted to talk about whether this is
across an event horizon is there are all
sorts of things which seem like of
course they will return and I have a
sense they will return at some level but
I also wonder if we look longer out
whether some of these things are just
finished some of these things are
finished but people saying people never
sit in restaurants again or go to live
theater I say you haven't met people
like that's that's those things aren't
over yeah they're not over on the other
hand I gotta tell you I don't know where
we are
I don't know how restaurants are safe
yep right they can't be safe if somebody
who coughs into a bowl of salad a big
bowl of salad they've made for the whole
restaurant can't throw it out because
they'll get fired so you've just
decreased salad consumption considerably
more for me yeah okay
a I don't know if this is a link I can't
quite tell not as not a question
Co but 19 lockdown risks 14 million
extra tuberculosis deaths study that
number seems like it couldn't possibly
be true but clearly there's a hypothesis
in here with regard to a lockdown
risking a lot of TB deaths I don't know
what the relationship is as premier is
clearly asking us to investigate it I
think we need to see more before we can
be expected to go hunting for this I
often have to keep a dictionary next to
me during these but I love feeding my
brain oh and then a cute sign of thank
you doctor and mr. Hein fairness is
there enough yes what does your younger
son what is your younger son do during
these live streams how do you guys
manage and limit screen time on various
devices for your kids
well of course general live streams we
have actually had no idea what Toby does
that's true now I mean this on this
particular live stream I know he he got
the potatoes in the oven so that we
would have something to go with the
amazing brisket from last night when we
when we get off here he sometimes goes
on an electric unicycle ride he no doubt
plays with the menagerie that we have
living with us did you just say electric
unicycle I did that sounds crazy I know
it is your circus music in my head what
else does he done what else does he do I
don't really know how do we manage and
limit screen time and various devices
for our kids this this again is probably
a whole a whole hours or more topic but
in some ways you know neither of our
kids had we didn't put we didn't enforce
hard and fast rules we tried to model
behavior that seemed right and kept them
from access neither them had smartphones
actually until he moved here so that
would have been or not even smartphones
at that fobian Toby hates it isn't when
I have a phone at all still but our
feeling is we live in a city now you got
to have one in case we need to get in
touch with you you need to get in touch
with us so you know everyone's got
screens now all of us have screens we
live among way too many screens
but yeah I would say you know we a we
delayed contact with things longer than
almost anybody we know when we have
granted contact we have tried to shape
that contact in a good direction so you
know our kids do watch some television
now but it's all with us things that
we've chosen that we think they oughta
see sometimes we may not choose
perfectly we know we're not used
perfectly in fact in this case with the
lockdown you know with the kids sort of
coming of age we showed them risky
business so they're now both men because
that's how it works
yes yeah that's how it works that's how
it works now but in any case yeah we try
to shape their their encounters with
this stuff and then we spend a lot of
time talking about what it means in the
hazards I guess I mean that's that's the
big thing and you know we we we have a
lot to say about this and also about
parenting and childhood more generally
but we've been I believe we actually
came to understand not too many years
ago that you and I both had
independently without ever talking about
it only not talked about one subject
with our children and we were otherwise
I mean you mentioned earlier sex drugs
and rock and roll like we talked about
it our best sex drugs and rock and roll
that's breakfast conversation and that's
not to say that it always makes them
totally comfortable always makes us
totally comfortable but we've been
pretty forthright about all sorts of
topics that most parents try to keep
from their children death you know I've
talked about my father's deaths on this
podcast night and that was episode six
and they were present for it and we
spoke a lot about what it meant to be
grieving it what it meant to be dead
they were present for it and they were
present for the actual start of the
cremation yeah
no point of it you know so there are a
number of topics that have are strangely
taboo in our culture that should not be
and while screens is not exactly in that
category we have also been you know very
we've talked with them explicitly about
when
we struggle when we spend or spending
too much time on screen and session I
guess I should rather than leave that as
a something for people to wonder about
the one topic that we both avoided
talking about with them until they were
until very recently I was suicide
yep but neither of us thought it was
wise to introduce that as a concept that
they should even have in their heads
until they were a little bit older and
they're now they've just last month they
turned 16 and 14 okay what's our time
Zack okay we're gonna do just a couple
more here and then we will it sounds
like the tech stuff is mostly resolved
so we should be back on Saturday the
duct tape and the baling wire have held
throughout to broadcast now so that's
good yeah just saying thanks your
presence is valuable thank you
regards from Poland is 3:00 a.m. here
hey man thank you I think this one is
gonna make you chuckle but aquatic ape
theory take it away you know I thought
you were gonna bring this up when you
started talking about other returns to
sea but it would have been tug and chic
because neither of us think so with this
you and I both I know I did always
whenever I was teaching for it about
evolution at least and sometimes and I
was doing a little behavior or some
other topics and students got to choose
their own research topics for for
literature review papers rather than
empirical research which we also did
often someone would research the aquatic
hypothesis it it being more or less that
the the east coast of Africa looked
different at the point that humans were
evolving and becoming fully human which
no it did and that we were basically
waiting around being somewhat aquatic
and that this explains a number of our
current anatomical physiological and no
doubt cultural features and it's silly I
don't I don't buy it
you know I sort of mirrors actually it
mirrors exactly this story yes the Bears
fishing about in the shallow Tethys sea
the more aquatic they became the more
effective they were at hunting yada yada
yada so anyway we get the argument it's
not like the argument doesn't work but
we just don't think the evidence
suggests that that's what happened
to humans greatness from Peru hey hola
are you familiar with Martin no ox no
wax eusociality research with ear wilson
yes
Nowak was just fired over Epstein ties
this I did not know think they ever
talked about neocon blackmail paddle
cults with regard to global human
eusociality there's a lot in that
question yeah Wow and Slartibartfast the
best to know I didn't know that Nowak
had been fired I'm not a fan of the work
that would have no AK and Wilson
overlapping I think they've both made an
error I had a conversation with Nowak
about this he's actually pretty nice guy
but nonetheless I don't think the group
selection is know where they are and how
they ended up there I think they have a
piece of the puzzle right but they have
a mechanism that isn't right and they
they have talked themselves into a
corner so anyway this is the group
selection discussion it does have to be
sorted out I do think that there's an
answer that's fairly straightforward and
is fully satisfying stay tuned okay
we've got three more questions two of
which are just comments so we'll get
through these and then we'll sign off
guys we can't afford to give up Trump
the oligarchy is worse you can have your
status quo candidates back in 2024
thanks for everything you do that's what
we want
we are shills for the status quo that's
what we're hoping for
look I actually I hear I hear this
person the guy yeah yep I hear you Scott
I really do and you know Heather will
back me up on this the night that Trump
was elected I told her he could be the
greatest president in history and he has
disappointed me primarily because he
didn't decide to do it I would have been
thrilled actually if he was willing
having done the impossible which was get
elected in that environment having done
the impossible if he had stepped up to
the plate and said you know what I'm
gonna be the greatest president in
history I would have been there to back
him but I mean this is exactly what you
were just saying with her
- his response right now right like he
he had just been handed a victory that
no one maybe not even hey he expected
and this he didn't expect he didn't want
he has no idea what to do etc but in
both cases he could have been behaving
in some way that's so stymied
expectations in the status quo that he
could actually have broken a lot of the
entrenched systems that are actually
breaking the rest of us yeah so Scott
let me just say he did the impossible
I think he deserves credit for having
done the impossible he broke through the
duopoly having broken through the de la
pelea his fatal flaw is that he cannot
step out of the political modality that
allowed him to do it and this is not
personal he can't be in that office any
longer why because the things that we
are playing with are so volatile so
dangerous that we need somebody who is
capable of putting their own interests
aside and it was his inability to put
his interests aside that'll actually
allowed him to win in 2016 so anyway
again it's not personal but we need
somebody there who's got the unusual
characteristics that will allow them to
to do the job in a way that all of us on
planet earth are depending on amazing
stuff guys thank you looking forward to
more info on how game B and 4th frontier
are going to take us away from oblivion
oh yeah final question can correcting
human evolutionary mismatch be a panacea
for society can we reconcile this with
modern rapid technological progress like
ancestral health org I'm not familiar
with that particular website but this
sounds like exactly the theme of the
book that we are working on a second
draft of right now we published about a
year from now yeah
so in short it's not too late as far as
we know it is not too late and there is
a way for human beings to grapple with
the novelty that we have created for
ourselves
said it's not simple it's not a
slam-dunk that we will get there and I
think at the core of your question is
the issue of whether or not individuals
solving their problem at their
individual scale scales up to solve the
global problem and it doesn't we have to
deal with this at each of those
intermediate scales and it's possible
but it's gonna be it's gonna be
interesting work but it's gonna be
difficult so let's get to it
all right all right well this has been
great and looks like some of our
technical issues have abated at least
for the moment and we will see you next
time